Guide to the Papers of Jules Backman 1938-1975 MC.123
New York University Archives
Jules Backman Papers
1938-1975
New York University Archives
Backman, Jules, 1910-1982
MC.123
10 Linear Feet (10 boxes)
This collection includes the personal files of Jules Backman, nationally known economist and expert on prices, accumulated during his tenure on the faculties of the School of Commerce, College of Business and Public Administration, and Graduate School of Business Administration (now the Stern School of Business). The records include lecture notes, working files, syllabi, and correspondence.
Scope and Content Note
This collection includes the personal files of Jules Backman. Records include lecture notes, working files, syllabi, and correspondence.
Historical/Biographical Note
Jules Backman, economist, author, and educator, was born in New York, NY on May 3, 1910. After attending high school in Brooklyn, he enrolled in NYU, where he would earn four degrees -- Bachelor of Commercial Science (1931), Master of Arts from the School of Education (1932), Master of Business Administration (1933), and Doctor of Commercial Science (1935). Three years after earning his PhD, Backman became an instructor in economics at NYU. He continued to serve on the faculties of the School of Commerce/College of Business Administration (now the Leonard N. Stern School of Business) from 1938 to 1975. As Professor Emeritus he continued to teach in an adjunct capacity.
Backman served as a consultant to major trade associations and corporations, particularly in steel, railroads, and retailing. He published widely on the subject of pricing. His books include Adventures in Price Fixing (1936), Administered Prices (1957), and Entrepreneurship and the Outlook for America (published posthumously in 1983).
Backman was also an active participant in the public sector. In 1935, President Franklin D. Roosevelt named him to the Securities and Exchange Commission. He worked in the Office of Price Administration in the early 1940s and was an adviser to the President's Cost of Living Committee. Subsequently, he served on state and local advisory groups, including the Governor's Commission on Milk Marketing, the New York Joint Legislative Committee on Rents, and as consultant to the U.S. General Accounting Office and the New Jersey Rate Counsel.
The founding president of the New York University Club, Backman made major contributions to NYU for both scholarships and capital improvements. He was active in Jewish community service as chairman of the Reform Jewish Appeal from 1966 to 1969 and chairman of the Board of Governors of Hebrew Union College/Jewish Institute of Religion from 1976 until his death in 1982.
Sources:
Backman, Jules, Biographical File, NYU Archives
Access Restrictions
Materials are open without restrictions.
Provenance
The collection was transferred to the University Archives in 1992 by Barbara Ring, Office of the Dean, Stern School of Business.
United States |x Economic policy.; Pricing.; Speeches.; Correspondence.; Advertising -- United States.; Syllabi.; Backman, Jules, 1910-1982; New York University. School of Commerce, Accounts, and Finance
- Series I: Topical Files
  - Acknowledgements, A-C, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    Barcode #: 3 1142 042261134
  - Advertising, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04226113 4
  - Administered Prices, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Antitrust, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Antitrust, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Submission Data, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Balance of Payments, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Budgets, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Budgets 2, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Carpetwage Case, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Columbia University, Arden House, Conferences, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Commendatory Letters, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Commendatory Letters, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Commendatory Letters, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Common Market, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Conglomerates, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Economics of NY State/Full Crew Laws, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Frozen Food, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Furniture, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Institute of Public Relations Cattle and Livestock Study, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Creeping Inflation, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Escalator Clauses, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Feather Bedding, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - FTC, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Food, British, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Future Growth, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Gov. Foods Conference, Advisor to Gov. Dewey, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Hardware, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Identical Bids, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Price Fixing & Price Shading, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Job Applications, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Joint Economic Committee Prices, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Kefauver Committee, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Life, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Loews, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Macy's, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Merck Hearing, undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Mergers, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04226114 2
  - NICV Courses - Economics for Executives, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Paper Cup and Container Institute, Inc., undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Penn Olin - Joint Ventures, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Penn State - Economic Growth, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Postal Pricing, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - President's Cost of Living Committee, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Price Control - J. Ingebretson - 1946 Extension, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Delivered Prices, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Price Index, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Pricing, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Price Leadership, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Price Data, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Price Index, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Prices, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Pricing Profits, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Productivity, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Productivity, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Productivity, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Professional Fees, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04226115 9
  - Profits - NCB Figures, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Purchasing Power Theory, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Rent Control, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Rent Control, Commercial, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Republican Nat. Committee, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Retail Trade - Learners, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Requests, Material, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - NYU Club, 1955-1956 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - NYU, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Requests by Students for Letters of Ref. RESTRICTED, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Requests, Library and Others for Publications, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Robinson - Patman, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Radio Talks, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Russia, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Society of Business Advisory Professions, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Subsidies, U.S., 1945 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Salk Price Leadership, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Smith, Alexander, 1951-1952 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Reference, Letters of RESTRICTED, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Students, Former RESTRICTED, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - TV, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Thesis, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Treble Damages, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Union Bag - Camp Paper Co., 1964 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - U.S. Potash, undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - U.S. Potash, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - U.N., Committee on Members from, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Wage Guarantees, undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Wage and Prices, Cost of Living Arguments, undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - WLB Wage Report to President, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Wage - Price Guidelines, undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Warner-Lambert, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Welfare Committee, NYU, undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Western Electric, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Western Electric Lecture, undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Radio Talks, undated (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Railroads, undated (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Surety Study, Comments & Requests, undated (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Surety, Testimony & Exhibits, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Surety, Testimony & Exhibits, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Shoe, undated (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Surety Recommendations, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04226116 7
  - Surety Miscellaneous, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Appendix, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Insurance Rate Making, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Surety & Insurance, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Surety Memos, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Addresses, 1975-1976 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Speeches, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Speeches, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Speeches, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Speeches, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Speeches, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Speeches, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Speeches, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Speeches, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Speeches, 1970-1977 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Speeches, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Japanese Speeches & Lecture Material, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Negro Revolution & Its Economic Impact, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Press Releases, 1962-1963 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Trip to Europe, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Trip to Israel & Europe (Roberts College Istanbul), 1961 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Articles, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Japan, undated (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - A-P, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04226117 5
  - American Thread Co., undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - American Enterprise Assoc. Subsidies - Prices, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - American Radiator, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - American Radiator, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Anaconda, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Atlantic City, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Atlantic City Testimony, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Bakery - Final Draft - Wages, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Banking - Memphis, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Baltimore, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Banking, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Banking, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Baron, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Benetar, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Benetar, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Benetar, 1975-1976 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Bethlehem Steel, undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Bloomingdales, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Boston Shoe, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - NYS Brewers Study, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Bristol Myers, undated (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Bristol Myers Asprin Study, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Carter-Wallace, undated (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Business Roundtable, undated (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - California and Hawaiian Sugar Co., 1968 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Chase Bag Co., undated (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - UN Study of Chemicals, undated (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Chemical Bank & Rockville Center Merger, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Chemical Bank Merger, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Chemicals, undated (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Cincinnati Anti-trust, 1967-1968 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - CG&E, 1971-1972 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Citizens, undated (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Cyclops, undated (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - City Investing Memoranda, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - City Service Co, Testimony, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Colonial Sugar Refining Co, Antitrust Brief, undated (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Continental Can, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Continental Steel, undated (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Continental Cont, 1950-1951 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Con-Ed, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Celanese Corp - Wage Case, undated (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Coal Case, 1949-1958 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Cement, 1970-1971 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Cement, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Coca-Cola, undated (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Crane, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Dan River, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04226118 3
  - Detroit Edison Co., 1962 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Double Leverage, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Druck, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - DuPont, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Drugs, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Drugs, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Drugs, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Economic Services, Inc - Drug Pricing, 1945 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Fidelity and Deposit, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - F&D Tables, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - F&D Set of Memoranda, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - F&D Testimony, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - FMC, undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - FMC, undated (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Florida Power, undated (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - FAT, undated (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Gemini Computer Systems, 1974-1975 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - General Telephone, 1962-1965 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - General Telephone, 1962-1965 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - General Telephone, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - General Telephone of California, undated (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - GPU, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Grayson Robinson Stores, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Handleman Study, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Hawaiian Sugar, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04226119 1
  - Hoffman, La Rocke, 1965-1966 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Hospitals, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Hospitals, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Hospitals, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Ingersoll-Rand, undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - ITT Comments, FTC Report, undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Insurance, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Irving Trust, undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Johnson & Johnson, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - JRM, undated (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - J&J, undated (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Mead Johnson, undated (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Meat Packing Industry, Economics of, undated (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Merck & Co, undated (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Meyer and Reis Rebuttals (NJ Bell), 1973 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Milk Testimony, undated (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Milk, undated (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - MA Hospital, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Miles Shoes, undated (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Morgan - Convenience, Needs & Welfare, undated (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Morgan Hearings, undated (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Morgan Guarantee Merger, undated (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Movies, 1948 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - NBC, undated (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Nathan Report, undated (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - National Furniture Review, undated (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - National Bureau of Economic Research, undated (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - National Marketing Advisory, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - NYC v Police & Firemen, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - New York State Dept. of Commerce, undated (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - NJ Bell, Rebuttal, 1973-1974 (Box 7, Folder 32)
  - Northwest Industries, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 33)
  - Parke-Davis, undated (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - Parke-Davis, undated (Box 7, Folder 35)
  - Parke-Davis, 1972-1974 (Box 7, Folder 36)
  - Penn-Dixie Cement Corp., undated (Box 7, Folder 37)
  - Penn-Dixie Cement, Interest Rates, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04226120 9
  - Post Office, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Publishers Association of New York, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Public Service, Tests & Exhibits, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Public Service, Memos, 1974-1975 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Public Service Electric & Gas, 1975 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Public Service, undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Pulp, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Realty Advisory Board, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Realty Advisory Board, 1948-1949 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Radio, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Rankin, James, undated (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Rapid Shoe, undated (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Reading, undated (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Rockland, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Sperry Rand Co., Treble Damage Case, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Steel, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Steel Scrap, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Steel, Strand Corp, 1963-1964 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Tanker, undated (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Technicon, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Toledo Edison, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Toledo Edison, Federal Power Commission Case, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Tobacco, undated (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Trade Secrets, 1973-1974 (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Unishops, Kessler Estates, 1975-1976 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04226121 7
  - USM, undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - United Fruit, 1957 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - US Line, RJ Reynolds Tobacco, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Westinghouse Broadcasting, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Ad Prices, undated (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Aluminum, undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Autos, undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Beer, undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Building Materials, undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Cans, undated (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Cement, undated (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Chemicals, undated (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Cigarettes, undated (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Computer Leasing, undated (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Construction, undated (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Copper, coal, zinc & allied Products - Metals, undated (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - John Maxwell, Advertising, undated (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - AIE - SEC UK, undated (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Electricity Rates, undated (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Farm Equipment, undated (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Film, undated (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Floor Coverings, undated (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Food Products, undated (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Glass, undated (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Liquor, undated (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Mortician Prices, undated (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - Oils, undated (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - Paints, undated (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - Paper Cup and Container Institute, Inc., undated (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - Photography, undated (Box 9, Folder 31)
  - Plastics, undated (Box 9, Folder 32)
  - Plumbing Fixtures, undated (Box 9, Folder 33)
  - Postal Rates, undated (Box 9, Folder 34)
  - Price Leadership, undated (Box 9, Folder 35)
  - Rubber Products, undated (Box 9, Folder 36)
  - Shipping, undated (Box 9, Folder 37)
  - Shoes, undated (Box 9, Folder 38)
  - Steel Price Increase, undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04226122 5
  - Steel, undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Steel - Price Cutting, undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Sugar, undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Textiles, undated (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - TV, Radio, and Records, undated (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Transportation Prices, undated (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Water Heaters, undated (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Wood Products, undated (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Untitled, undated (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Bibles, undated (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Advertising/Anti-Trust, undated (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Advertising - Speeches, undated (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - List for A&C Book, undated (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - A&C Reviews, undated (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - AAAA, 1967 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - AMA, undated (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Advertising, John Maxwell, undated (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - AIE - SEC UK, undated (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - NYU Club, 1967 (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Survey of Current Business, undated (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - Monthly Economic Letters, undated (Box 10, Folder 22)